<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new discouery of personal tithes: or The tenth part of mens cleere gaines Proued due both in conscience, and by the lawes of this kingdome. By C. Burges.</title>
            <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113879</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849108</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14242</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 632:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new discouery of personal tithes: or The tenth part of mens cleere gaines Proued due both in conscience, and by the lawes of this kingdome. By C. Burges.</title>
                  <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. L[egat] for William Sheffard, and are to be sold at his shop, at the entring in of Popes-head Aley, out of Lumbard street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14242:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW DISCOVERY OF PERSONAL TITHES: OR The TENTH PART of Mens CLEERE GAINES Proued due both in CONSCIENCE, and by the LAWES OF THIS KINGDOME <hi>BY</hi> C. BVRGES.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>William Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the entring in of Popes head Alley, out of Lumbard ſtreet. 1625</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:14242:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14242:2"/>
            <head>APPROBATIO.</head>
            <p>HVnc Librum de <hi>DECI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MIS PERSONALIBVS,</hi> à <hi>CORNELIO BVRGES</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae Majeſtati à Sacris editum, perlegit, expendit, &amp; vt Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Orthodoxum, Vtilemque, approbavit</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>TH: WORRAL,</hi> S S. Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae Profeſſor, <hi>GEORGIO</hi> Domino Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo <hi>LONDIN.</hi> a Sacris Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticis, Libro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Cenſor Deputatus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14242:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14242:3"/>
            <head>READER, Some Aduertiſements.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> REade All, or reade nothing.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Pardon me that I take not vp that Principal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon of this Warfare: viz. <hi>Ius Diuinum</hi> My Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue often done that; but, <hi>Heu!</hi> (ſuch is the hardneſſe of mens hearts,) with a <hi>Satis parum</hi> of fruit.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> To that Tenet J ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe affirmatiuely, <hi>ex a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo:</hi> but with Cautions. <hi>1.</hi> Tithes (J ſay not, ought elſe) are due by <hi>Diuine
<pb facs="tcp:14242:4"/> Right</hi> to Ministers of the Goſpel. <hi>2.</hi> I neuer was, nor (J thinke) euer ſhall be of opinion, that, <hi>All Tithes within ſuch, or ſuch a circuit of Ground, now by Poſitiue Law made but one Pariſh, are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, and without al exception, due by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Right to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of one ſingle Incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent there, but to the Church, in whoſe name he receiueth them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The Reaſon of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing that Argument, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, is bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe Joam to deale with men, that elſe would complaine of <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb facs="tcp:14242:4"/> the Queſtion,</hi> and that I diſpute <hi>ex non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſis.</hi> No diſputation will yeeld good fruit, vnleſſe ſome Principles vndeniable on all bands bee held, to cut off all Difficulties which all Diſputes will produce.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Though the <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> vndertaken be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>mine,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et the <hi>Premiſſes</hi> bee as properly <hi>theirs</hi> with whom J diſpute. Nothing therefore can be left to deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, vnleſſe the Concluſion And who ſo denieth that, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies obedience both to God and Man. This (being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) will take off the asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Couetouſneſſe,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly
<pb facs="tcp:14242:5"/> caſt vpon the Miniſter by the Mammoniſts; and iuſtly cauſe it to fall vpon himſelf for denying payment of what the Lawes both of God and Man haue made due to his Paſtor; wherein he breakes ſixe of the <hi>Ten Commaundements</hi> at once: <hi>viz.</hi> The ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, by Sacriledge: the fourth Commandement, by denying the meanes of ſanctifying the Sabbath: the fifth Commandement, by diſhonoring his Spirituall Father: the ſixth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, by cauſing (as much as in him lies) his Minister to periſh for want of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance:
<pb facs="tcp:14242:5"/> the eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, by robbing the Miniſter of his iust dues: and the ninth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by bearing falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe against his neighbour; vniuſtly accuſing the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Couetouſnes, which is indeed the proper ſinne of himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Jf J be not ſo preſſe; and <hi>Sylogiſticall</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as ſome may expect, conſider that J intended this Worke principally to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar Capacities, whom it chiefely concernes. And in dealing with ſuch, the <hi>Palme</hi> is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Fiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Jn ſtead of <hi>Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14242:6"/> J often vſe the word, <hi>Paſtor;</hi> not as better, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, or including therein an Epiſcopal Authority; but as more distinct, facile, and plaine to ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings that J write vnto.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> Jf the Diſtinction of <hi>Perſonall,</hi> and <hi>Prediall</hi> Tithes, ſeem heathen Greek, take notice; That <hi>Predial</hi> Tythes are ſuch as ariſe out of the Ground; as Corne, Hay, increaſe of all kinds of Cattle, Fowles, Fruit, &amp;c. <hi>Perſonal,</hi> are ſuch as grow out of the lawfull gaines got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by any Art, Science, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Occupation, Trade, Merchandize, &amp;c. of any Perſon or Perſons.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb facs="tcp:14242:6"/>
               <hi>9.</hi> That J fall to <hi>Moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing,</hi> and expoſition of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, is not wholly incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The Subiect is <hi>mixt.</hi> And though the Roofe, and Battlements be of <hi>Law,</hi> yet the Ground-cell, and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is <hi>Diuinity.</hi> No man can finiſh this Pile, without ſome help from both Profeſsions. The Lawyer cannot doe it, without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon our ground: Nor wee, without the like vpon His. He hath begun; therefore let him allow the ſame liberty to vs, to build a Buttreſſe or two vpon his Free-hold, the better to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port our Building.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14242:7"/>
            <p>Why not? Haue not Two Great Masters, one of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi> the other of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>non</hi> Law, amongst vs, taken their pleaſure in our Walkes, and handled Subiects meerely <hi>Theologicall?</hi> Such Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents will, J hope, make that pardonable to me, which ſome thinke, is matter of Praiſe to them. <hi>Yes:</hi> (will you ſay,) <hi>if you come off well.</hi> Goe to, then. Conſider, and Cenſure:
<q>
                  <l>—Sed magis acri</l>
                  <l>Iudicio perpendé, &amp; ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b I vera videtur,</l>
                  <l>Dede manus: aut, ſi falſa eſt, accingere contra.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Some letters and points omitted, tranſplaced, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t redundant; correct, or pardon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14242:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A NEVV DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVERY OF PERSONAL</hi> TITHES, Prouing that <hi>EVERY</hi> Perſon within this Kingdome vſing any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, Art, Science, Handy craft, Trade, Merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, Buying, Selling, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering any Goods, Wares, or Commodities by which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lawfull Gaines are made, is bound both in Conſcience, and by the Lawes of this Realme, to pay the <hi>TENTH</hi> part of all his cleere Gaines
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14242:8"/> (as a due debt) to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſſe ſome, ſpeciall Cuſtome, Compoſition, or Priuiledge of the Place where he liues allowed by Law, exempt him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</head>
            <p>BEfore I enter vpon the proofe of this Propoſition, I craue leaue to profeſſe 3. things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That my Purpoſe is not here to fall vpon that Queſtion, (for I make no Queſtion of it) Whether Tithes be perpetually due to the Miniſters of the Goſpell by <hi>Diuine Right:</hi> nor to fetch any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from that Tenet to proue the point in hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That I intend not the Iuſtification, in point of equitie, of Perſons lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14242:8"/> hold on the Cuſtomes, or Priuiledges of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they liue, to pay little, or nothing: but to leaue their practiſes and conſciences to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by ſuch as are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to plead for them, and are willing to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained in ſo doubtfull a Cauſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That my chiefe ayme in this diſcourſe is (if it be poſſible) to pull ſundry honeſt Chriſtians out of a damnable ſinne, whereof perhaps many of them neuer dream't; which knowing and conſidering of as I do, I hold my ſelfe bound in conſcience to make <hi>Diſcouery</hi> thereof vnto them, leaſt I be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their ſinne, and their blood.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14242:9"/>
            <p>The Arguments on which the <hi>Propoſition</hi> vndertaken is originally grounded, (as I intend now to confirme it,) are drawne from theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Corinth. <hi>9.13, 14.</hi>
                  </bibl> Doe yee not know that they which miniſter about ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly things, liue of the things of the Temple? And they which waite at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar? Euen ſo hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould liue of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 6.6.</hi>
                  </bibl> Let him that is taught in the word, make him that taught him partaker of all his goods.</p>
            </q>
            <p>From theſe Scriptures I deduce theſe foure vndenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Concluſions: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14242:9"/>1. That God hath as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and firmely taken order for the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he did for the Prieſts &amp; Leuites in time of the Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That their maintenance muſt ariſe from, and out of whatſoeuer the People haue by the bleſſing of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their labours in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Callings.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That euery man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed muſt communicate to his Teacher; be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed mans Calling what it will; and that what hee communicates in this kinde is not a free Contribution, or voluntary bounty, but a <hi>due debt</hi> impoſed by God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That God hauing thus prouided for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Miniſter, Euery Paſtor performing his duty,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14242:10"/> may iuſtly demaund a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euery mans goods whom he inſtructeth; and that as his proper Portion appointed by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>No intelligent man durſt abſolutely to deny any of theſe Concluſions, for ſubſtance yet there are who make ſome Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtions, touching ſome pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticulars in them, as they are laid for grounds pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a <hi>Tenth</hi> due from men vſing Trade, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Queſtions are Two: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether, if a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter haue a Competencie out of Praediall Tythes: that is, of the Profits of the Ground; A Man that lines by Trading be bound of due to giue as much to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14242:10"/> as if he had not ſuch a Competencie from other men?</hi> And</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If euery Tradeſ-man muſt pay; then, whether he be bound to pay a Tenth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Queſtions will be beſt reſolued to euery mans capacitie and ſatisfaction, by propounding and anſwering the vſuall Plea's which men make againſt my Poſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If a Miniſter (ſay ſome) haue a Competent liuing out of Praediall Tithes in kinde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Plea.</note> 
               <hi>or by Compoſition, which he may recouer by Law from ſuch as deale in Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry; then, ſuch as liue vpon Trade, or other Bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or Manu-facture are not bound to allow him more then the Lawes of the Kingdome enioyne; or at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14242:11"/> leaſt, not ſo much as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> To this I anſwere thus: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe I deſire to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide wrangling and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſputes, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince theſe men by their owne Rules; I will, for the preſent, admit, that, if the Miniſter haue a Competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ariſing from Tithes, Tradeſmen are not bound to make a larger allowance then the Lawes of the Realme binde them vnto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet, ſo much as the Lawes require of them they muſt pay, what euer his maintenance ariſing from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers amounteth vnto.</p>
            <p>This laſt appeares thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let him that is taught out</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14242:11"/> 
               <hi>of the Word, &amp;c.</hi> that is, euery Hee, none excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; vnleſſe him that hath nothing to giue. If others giue, and I thinke by that to be excuſed, how doe I obey the Apoſtles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept which excludes none but them that haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? If a Miniſter might not require maintenance of the Tradeſman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath enough from others in Praediall Tithes, it would follow, that if he had a Temporal eſtate of his owne ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to maintaine him, he could not iuſtly demaund any Tithes at all: which I thinke no man (well in his wits) would affirme. For, <hi>Who goeth a warfare at any time at his owne charge? Who planteth a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14242:12"/> Vine-yard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not of the milke of the flocke?</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man therefore that is made partaker of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>Spirituals,</hi> muſt render <hi>Carnals.</hi> verſe 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Admit a Miniſter may by Law recouer a maintenance without the Tenth of the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans encreaſe, yet it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happens that a good part of his meanes (if he liue in a Country Towne eſpecially) ariſeth out of the ſmall Tithes and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the Poore who ſtand in daily neede of Almes from him. In this caſe, will any conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſtian thinke, that ſo long as ſuch petty dues
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14242:12"/> may be by Law extorted from the poore, he ſhould rather take this courſe to be maintained, then call to rich Tradeſmen for ſuch a portion as may fill vp that Competencie which is made vp by the Poore? Should not thoſe Tradeſmen holde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bound to yeeld him ſo much as that hee may rather be able to giue to the poore, then enforced to pull the poore mans bread out of his belly, to ſaue the rich mans purſe?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſe ſuch as vſe husbandry ſhould thinke (as our <hi>Taske-maſters</hi> would perſwade them) that in reſpect of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of conſcience and equitie, they are free by Gods word from paying
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14242:13"/> Tithes, and ſo deny pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Tradeſman doth: how then ſhall the Miniſter haue his Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie raiſed?</p>
            <p>I know to this it will bee anſwered by a Tradeſman: That the Parliament which hath abſolute power to ſet a part what portion it will of all mens goods for any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good vſe, hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bandmen ſhall yeeld the Tenth of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to the Miniſter for his ſeruice: and therefore if the Husbandman deny pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there is Law to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell him.</p>
            <p>True. But of him that would haue vs plead Law to the Husbandman, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund; whether hee doe thinke that Lawe of the Kingdome to be equall, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14242:13"/> ſuch as the Husbandman is bound in Conſcience to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, conſidering that Hee ſeeth Tradeſmen (who ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with more eaſe get as much in one yeare, as hee with all his toyle can gather in fiue,) take themſelues not to be ſtrictly bound to pay any thing, (as Tradeſmen,) but two pence at Eaſter? And if we vrge them with conſcience, they retort a captious anſwere; Why ſhould not the Magiſtrates conſcience (who hath left vs at liberty,) bee as good as yours? One of theſe two therefore, muſt bee yeelded and confeſſed; Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Law of the Land is iuſt, and good; or elſe vniuſt, and without warrant from the Word of God.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14242:14"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt part of the <hi>Dilemma.</hi>
               </note>Firſt, If the Lawe bee graunted to be <hi>iuſt, and good</hi> in this caſe, then it muſt bee confeſſed that there is both equitie, and ſtrength ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to binde the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in conſcience to ſubmit vnto it; and to aſſure the Miniſter that he may with a good conſcience preſſe it vpon him, if he refuſe it. If there bee any equitie in this Law (as doubtleſſe there is) it conſiſteth in this, that <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals doe well deſerue Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</hi> And if this equitie will hold to bind the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man when God bleſſeth him with any increaſe, let any man ſhew me a reaſon, why he ſhould pay ſo much of his Carnals for Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als; and not the Tradeſman whom God hath bleſſed with Carnals as much, or more.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14242:14"/>
            <p>If it be ſaid, <hi>the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath Tithes; and the Tradeſ-man, none.</hi> This alters not the caſe in reſpect of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of maintaining the Paſtor, in the Tradeſmans iudgement: for he doth not hold Tithes to bee the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per conſtant and fitteſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, by <hi>Diuine Right;</hi> but ſtrikes in with ſome of the Papiſts, and Browniſts and ſome others of late time (who, herein, daunce all in a ring;) and auoucheth that they are now due vpon another ground, namely by vertue of the Magiſtrates Law only. Therefore the Tradeſman cannot plead this as a reaſon why in equitie the Husbandman ſhould pay ſo much, and himſelfe ſo little.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14242:15"/>
            <p>The equitie of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Law in reſpect of the Husbandman is this. Hee partakes of Gods bleſſing in Temporals, therefore it is iuſt hee ſhould returne vnto God a portion thereof for the maintenance of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters who <hi>ſow vnto him Spirituals.</hi> Now, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but reach all ſorts of men, ſo bleſſed, as well as any. Vnto all men it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, <hi>Honour God with thy ſubſtance, and with the firſt fruits of all thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. Prou.</hi> 3.9. If any thinke, this held only in the time of the Law, or that it was ſpoken only to Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, let him conſider whether this agreeth not in all points to the Apoſtles peremptory co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund more then once preſſed in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14242:15"/> Goſpel, and that not to Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, but to Citizens and Tradeſmen in the Cities of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and <hi>Galatia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Tradeſman wil yet plead, that <hi>his Profeſsion is Caſuall, and he often loſeth more then he gets?</hi> Will the Miniſter beare a part in his loſſes?</p>
            <p>I anſwere that this Plea becomes none but an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme who makes <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> his God.</p>
            <p>For, 1. So doth the Husbandman loſe too, and yet payes Tythes of what remaines: which if hee ſhould not doe, the Miniſter might ſtarue for want of a maintenance iuſtly due vnto him by the Tradeſmans Rule. So courteous ſome of out hot Profeſſors are to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14242:16"/> their Paſtors whom they admire moſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath no increaſe, he is not bound to pay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: yet is hee ſtill (if he be able) bound to help maintaine his Miniſter, if he be in want. This hee is tyed vnto by the Rule of Charitie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Miniſter when hee calles for his gaines, doth not call for them in the way of <hi>Partner-ſhip;</hi> but as <hi>a due for Spirituals,</hi> enioyned by Law accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Law hath ſet out no allowance of any thing but of encreaſe, yet the Miniſter takes no leſſe paines when the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man looſeth, then when he gaineth. And will the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14242:16"/> bountifull Tradeſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> think it equitie, not only (in that caſe) to let the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter worke for nothing; but require him to pay backe part of his iuſt dues formerly receiued; or elſe reſolue not to pay him of his gaines at all: If the Tradeſman ſinke follow in his eſtate that hee cannot ſubſiſt, the Miniſter (I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not) if he be able, is bound to helpe him; or otherwiſe, to ſtirre vp o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ſupply the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of their decayed Brother.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Miniſter hath warrant from the word to partake of his increaſe: but the Tradeſman hath no warrant from God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man to indent with his Paſtor to beare part of his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14242:17"/> loſſes, if he will receiue a part of his gaines. <hi>The labourer is worthy of his hire.</hi> And Spirituals de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue Carnals whether a man be a gainer or not. And he that is of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinion, I know not wherein (vnleſſe in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, which makes the matter worſe,) he differs from a <hi>Gadarine</hi> who loues a good heard of ſwine better then Chriſt. If they looſe their ſwine, let Chriſt goe ſeeke his maintenance where he can get it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma.</hi>
               </note>Secondly, If the Lawes of the Kingdome; enacted by the King and the whole Body of the Kingdome, be not iuſt and agreeable to the Word in binding the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14242:17"/> to payment of Tithes, How can a Miniſter with a good conſcience lay hold on it for his mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from the Husb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſo as not to neede the Tradeſmans helpe? How can the Tradeſmen ſtand ſtill &amp; looke on their poore Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too heauy laden, &amp; they (<hi>Phariſee</hi> like) not ſtoope to eaſe him with one of their fingers? How can they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, and put their Miniſter to ſue Husbandmen for Tithes, ſo as to carue out his whole maintenance out of their eſtates, and the meane while themſelues ſuppoſe they are not in iuſtice bound to doe any thing; or not to pay in proportion halfe ſo much as the others: and that which they doe, muſt be proclaimed and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14242:18"/> not a <hi>due,</hi> or iuſt pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>free Contributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a gift, a beneuolence which they holde themſelues no way bound vnto? This is neither agreeable to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, nor conſcience, nor Law, nor humanitie: and it would better befit an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, then a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Thus of the firſt maine Plea which Tradeſmen vrge to proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelus not bound to pay any thing (aboue their 2. d.) for their gaines in Trading as a due, where the Paſtor hath a mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance out of other mens <hi>Pradiall</hi> Tithes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Plea.</note>But now, ſuppoſe the Tradeſman co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced that he muſt <hi>pay proportionably to others;</hi> yet How can it bee proued to him who denyeth Tithes to be now
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14242:18"/> due by Diuine Right, <hi>that he is bound in conſcience to pay the Tenth part of all his cleere gaines?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He will plead, <hi>I giue as much and more then the Law enioyneth: as much as I am well able to ſpare: more then many, worth fiue of me, doe allow: as much as I ſuppoſe my ſelfe bound in conſcience to giue: and more then my Paſtor can in ſtrictneſſe require, or reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> To this I anſwere. That euery mans conſcience may ſtand vpon a firme ground, it muſt bee guided in euery thing by <hi>a ſure Rule.</hi> The Rule in this particular, is either the <hi>expreſſe Word</hi> of God; or elſe the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Law of the Kingdome</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a man liues, to which (if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14242:19"/> it contradict not the Diuine Law of God himſelfe,) eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon is bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>as vnto the Lord,</hi> and that vnder paine of <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 13.2.</note> Hee that liues in a well gouerned State muſt not walke by the guide of his owne fancie, and conceit, or by the Opinions of ſome <hi>Good</hi> men, or by the practiſe of ſuch as are behind him in eſtate, and eminent for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion: but he muſt keepe to his Rule, or hee damnably ſinneth. A good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, finding ſuch controuerſie about the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Portion, will ſooner ſuſpect his owne heart of couetouſneſſe, then his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; eſpecially if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor be one that performeth his dutie. Nor will he take liberty to ſuſpend his pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14242:19"/> till the Title bee clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: but knowing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he muſt doe, (yet ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how much;) he will rather giue too much, then too little, for feare of enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his conſcience. And, if there be any Rule, hee will follow it to an haire, what euer it coſt him, rather then hazard the peace of his heart.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a man to bee perplexed in conſcience about this point. He ſees <hi>a Portion of all his goods</hi> is due by Gods Command; nor can hee haue any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Reaſon, to deny, or euade it. Yet, for the <hi>definite Quantitie</hi> hee can finde no order, taken in all the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> whether it be there to bee found, or not. This hee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14242:20"/> knowes; Tithes were once paid not only <hi>to Leui,</hi> but <hi>by Leui</hi> in the <hi>loynes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.9, 10. Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.22.</note> And if God had not commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this as a duty: yet thoſe holy Patriarchs thought it their dutie to doe as much voluntarily, for the bleſſings of God receiued. Thoſe Tithes had nothing to doe with <hi>Leuies</hi> Prieſthood, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to it, no depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on it. Thence a tender conſcience may iuſtly thus reaſon the caſe. <hi>Though ſome men hold Tithes to bee no longer due then</hi> Leuies <hi>Prieſthood en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, and peremptorily deny that before</hi> Leui <hi>any Tithes were paid by com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maund from God; yet I fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e they were paid, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14242:20"/> accepted: Since men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree touching euery mans particular duty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and that Holy men (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Leui) <hi>though they had (as it ſeemes to me) no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Rule did pay the Tenth of all; whether ſhall I flie in this my distreſſe to pacifie and ſettle my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for time past, and to guide it ſafely for time to come? If there were from the beginning no particular diu ne Rule, nor at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent there were any ſuch, for the Quantitie due; yet if I were left to mine owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, can I haue better Preſidents then two ſuch Patriarcks before the Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Law? Or may I ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (notwithſtanding thoſe examples, and the iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the whole Church
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14242:21"/> of Chriſt for aboue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares,) gouerne my ſelfe by the Lawes of the State in which I liue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I aske now, in the Name of God, how I, or any Man elſe ſhould ſatisfie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue this mans Conſcience in ſuch a perplexity? Will you haue mee to ſay vnto him, as the bloody Prieſts to <hi>Iudas; What is that to vs? Looke thou to that?</hi> Shall I tell him, <hi>You were beſt keepe your mony till you ſee all men agree herein among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues;</hi> when he is tortured in ſoule out of feare he hath detained it too long alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die? Or ſhall I bid him <hi>vſe his owne diſcretion, and to giue what hee thinkes in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hee is well able to ſpare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ought to giue?</hi> This is cold comfort: poore reliefe.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14242:21"/> Hee is almoſt at his wits end for truſting ſo much to his owne diſcretion already. This is the ground of his trouble, that hee hath fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed his owne corrupt heart, and not any certaine and infallible Rule. And if a Tenth proue due by any Law ſufficient to bind him,<note place="margin">See the Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Reader Num. 5.</note> he ſhall but encourage him to ſteale, yea to commit <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and many other ſinnes of a high nature who ſhall bid him giue only that which hee is well able to ſpare; though leſſe then a Tenth.</p>
            <p>The Law of God hath made ſomething a debt to the Miniſter; and, if this Man hath not fully paid that due, it is not what he is <hi>well able to doe,</hi> that ſhall alwaies ſerue his turne before God,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14242:22"/> when he will take vpon him to be the ſole Iudge to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Debts muſt be paid, though the Debtor will not confeſſe himſelfe well able to ſpare them. And to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, <hi>what hee is well able to ſpare,</hi> will be a worke as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult as the other.</p>
            <p>None of all theſe waies then will proue ſufficient to direct a doubtful and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Conſcience. Nor doe I know any in the World ſoundly to reſolue, and guide that Conſcience, but one of theſe two: <hi>viz.</hi> I muſt bid him either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Looke into the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſearch what hath bin paid of old by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, before the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall Prieſthood; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then enſnare thy ſelfe, follow thoſe Examples till it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14242:22"/> be made cleere vnto thee by ſure Grounds that thoſe Payments were neither en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned; nor, in equitie, due; nor that any in Conſcience is bound now to doe the like.</hi> or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Haue recourſe to the establiſhed Lawes of the whole State and Kingdome wherein thou liueſt, (who haue abſolute power to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point and ſet out what Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they pleaſe of euery mans eſtate for any Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Vſe, and euery one is bound in Conſcience to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame): And looke what the Lawes (thus rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) enioyne, that thou muſt doe, or be a Rebell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some Mammoniſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, ſuſpecting whether he may be drawne by yeelding that to be a Due, which the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14242:23"/> Law of the Kingdome hath ſetled vpon the Miniſter, would bee ready to ſay; <q>I promiſe you, I doubt whether the Magiſtrate hath Power to enioyne Payment of Tithes, ſeeing Good Men, and Great Clerkes hold Tithes to be ſo Iewiſh, and Leuiticall that they were to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed together with the Ceremoniall Law; and that the Magiſtrate ſhould appoint ſome other Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</q> Now welfare <hi>Browniſt.</hi> What if in the Law, Tithes were Leuites Maintenance, may not that Maintenance be made ouer to another Order of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, when Leui was degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? May not mony once offered at the <hi>ſhrine</hi> of ſome Popiſh Saint, neuer be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14242:23"/> appointed or imployed to any other vſe? If this were ſound Diuinitie, many of thoſe ill-willers to Tithes ſhould be much more afraid how they touch any mony, but that which comes new from the Mint, leaſt (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) it be ſuch as formerly hath beene offered to ſome Romane Idol, and ſo it ſhould pollute them to vſe it, or touch it. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any thing comming towards them, they <hi>aske no Queſtion, for Conſcience ſake:</hi> therefore this, in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (though the ſame with the other,) ſhall paſſe for a Toy.</p>
            <p>But touching Tithes which is a ſweet morſell that they are loath to part with: Is there any thing in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or nature of Tithes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14242:24"/> that Legally typified Chriſt? If there bee, name it, and proue it, and you ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what. Otherwiſe, All you could inferre from that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd graunt of Tithes to be ſolely and properly Leuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Maintenance, would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount but to this Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; <hi>Tithes giuen to Leui for ſeruing at the Altar, may not by any Power of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate bee ſtill continued to Maintaine a Leuiticall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit, God, though he hath diſmiſſed Leui, and repealed that Law of Tithes due to Leui; yet hauing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, that <hi>(as they that ſerued at the Altar ſhould liue of the Altar, ſo) they which preach the Goſpel ſhould liue of the Goſpel;</hi> A Godly State (not taking vpon them
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14242:24"/> to be wiſer then Hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the old Teſtament: or his Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the New) will thus reſolue: <q>Wee cannot poſſibly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſitter Maintenance (all inconueniences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) for Miniſters now, then God did of old for the Leuites; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee will ordaine the ſame Quantitie ſhall now bee paide out of euery mans eſtate to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, whoſe Miniſtry being more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, their allowance ſhould not in equitie bee leſſe then that of Leui.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If it were a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to proue Tithes not lawfull or fit to bee now paid, becauſe once imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to maintaine Leuites; It muſt be preſſed, much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14242:25"/> vpon the Magiſtrate, that he is bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to pull down all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, once ſuperſtitiouſly proſtituted to Popiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, not ſuffering them to bee now vſed for the true worſhip of God. But hee that ſhould vrge this, would manifeſtly declare to all the World his iuſt Title to Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam.</p>
            <p>It may be, Some are of opinion that <hi>Chriſtians are now at liberty from ſuch Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, ſo as a man may vſe his owne diſcretion, and giue what hee thinkes fit.</hi> But to this ſomething hath beene ſaid before, to which now I adde; that this were the high way to become <hi>ſonnes of Belial</hi> indeed. We know how it went with Iſrael when <hi>there was no King</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14242:25"/> among them, and <hi>euery man did as it ſeemed good in his owne eyes.</hi> This indeede is that many Profeſſors would haue: Liberty, Liberty. Let them be noted for bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; but not bound to bee iuſt. What would become of Miniſters, (ſhall I ſay, nay), of themſelues, if this gap ſhould bee opened to the World that <hi>Chriſtians may doe as themſelues ſee good?</hi> Who would not <hi>abuſe his liberty as an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What though a few Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men would pay their Dues iuſtly, although no Law of man ſhould bee made: muſt their Honeſty make the World of opinion that they ought not to bee bound to a Law? Would not euery man plead the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14242:26"/> like; and ſo all would come ſoone to a confuſion? Can any of thoſe Honeſt Men proue that the Magiſtrate hath no Power to rule them herein? Should not they rather for examples ſake (though they might plead freedome) be firſt in yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding obedience to Lawes, euen for their ſakes who would neuer do iuſtly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Lawes to enforce them?</p>
            <p>Hath God bounded out all mens eſtates by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Lawes; and hath he left only Miniſters to Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Diſcretion and good Pleaſure, ſo as the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may not appoint them a certaine Portion, as to his Wiſedome ſhall ſeeme moſt conuenient, and agreeable to the Lawes of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? Oh Sonnes of Belial
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14242:26"/> that thus Proſtitute Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to palliate their coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe? The Couetous Earth-worme would laugh in his ſleeue to ſee his elbow vnderlaid with ſuch a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. The Licentious Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant would ſoone bring the Miniſter to his becke, and force him, Fidler-like, to play nothing but what Hee, and his lewd companions ſhould pleaſe to call for; or make Him to begge his bread from Dore to Dore. And are theſe the beſt Rules our beſt Zealots would walke by? Then, Who would not pray; God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend mee from the Power, and Courteſie of all ſuch Profeſſors? Should not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts (if this were allowed) haue iuſt cauſe to apply vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs that bitter Taunt,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14242:27"/> 
               <hi>Pater-Noſter</hi> ſet vp Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and <hi>Our Father</hi> puls them downe?</p>
            <p>The Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, then, is the only ſure Refuge of all that deny Tithes to be a Morall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. This is the only Rule they haue in all other Reformed Churches and States (hauing Power to make Lawes) throughout Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Admit this for this time to be a ſufficient Rule; and it muſt be graunted that, <hi>The Lawes of this Kingdome eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Parliament doe bind men both for Quantitie and Qualitie of the Miniſters Maintenance: And hee that doth not ſtrictly obſerue it, can neuer haue a good Conſcience, becauſe hee ſwerues from the Rule of his owne chooſing.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:14242:27"/> Whatſoeuer is of force as a Rule of Faith to iuſtifie the Conſcience walking by it, is alſo ſufficient to bind the Conſcience; and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him of ſinne that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth from it.</p>
            <p>Let the Tradeſman wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle and wriggle till he bee weary, this Rope will hold him. Now graunt mee this, and graunt all I vndertooke to prooue: <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Euery Perſon within this Kingdome (not liuing in Places Priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged) is bound to pay the Tenth of all his cleere Gaines to his Miniſter.</hi> For, this is the Law of this Kingdome ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the 2. and 3. yeares of <hi>Edward the ſixth, cap.</hi> 13. Entituled, <hi>An Act for the true Payment of Tithes.</hi> In which Statute is ordained as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14242:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And be it further enacted by the Authoritie aforeſaid, that euery Perſon exerciſing Merchandizes, Bargaining and Selling, Cloathing, Handy-craft, or other Art or Faculty, being ſuch kind of Perſons, and in ſuch kind of Places as heretofore within theſe <hi>40.</hi> yeares haue accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably vſed to pay, ſuch Perſonall Tithes, or of right ought to pay, other then ſuch as bee Common day Labourers, ſhall yearely at or before the Feaſt of Eaſter, pay for his Perſonall Tithes the Tenth part of his cleere Gaines; his charges and expences according to his eſtate, condition or degree to be therein abated, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and deducted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this it will be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obiected, Doe you not marke that clauſe, that men ſhall pay Perſonall Tithes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14242:28"/> 
               <hi>in ſuch kinde of places as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore within theſe <hi>40.</hi> yeares they haue accuſtomably vſed to pay ſuch Perſonall Tithes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> I doe:<note place="margin">This is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated.</note> and pray you to obſerue that which followes: <hi>viz.</hi> or of Right ought to pay.</p>
            <p>Some, perhaps, are in hope this will proue ſuch a Gordian knot, as will neuer be vntyed. But to put them by that vaine ſhift, let them know that this will eaſily be expounded (to the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch as deſire the truth may appeare;) partly by <hi>Other Parts</hi> of the ſame Statute; and partly by the Maine <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Scope</hi> of the Whole.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. By other parts of <hi>the Statute.</hi>
               </note> By other branches of the Statute it will appeare who they be that (not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing paid Perſonall Tithes,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14242:29"/> yet <hi>(of Right out to pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Fraction af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that branch of the Statute here alleadged, it is ſaid; <hi>Prouided alwaies and be it enacted that in all ſuch places where</hi> Handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts-men <hi>haue vſed to pay their Tenthes within theſe</hi> 40. <hi>yeares, the ſame cuſtome of payment of Tithes to bee obſerued and to continue.</hi> And a little after: <hi>Prouided that this Act ſhall not extend to any Pariſh which ſtands vpon and toward the Sea coaſts, the Commodities and occupying whereof conſiſteth chiefly in fiſhing, and haue by reaſon thereof vſed to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their Tithes by Fiſh but that all and euery ſuch Pariſh and Pariſhes ſhall hereafter pay their Tithes according to the laudable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes as they haue hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ancient time within theſe</hi> 40. <hi>yeares vſed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14242:29"/>
            <p>And againe: <hi>Prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies and be it enacted that this Act or any thing therein contained ſhall not extend in any wiſe to the Inhabitants of the Citie of</hi> London, <hi>and</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of the ſame: ne to any other Towne or Places that haue vſed to pay their Tithes by their houſes, otherwiſe then they ought or ſhould haue done before the making of this Act.</hi> Laſtly, there is an exception of the Tith of Marriage goods in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe Exceptions do aboundantly expound that clauſe who they are, that <hi>in right ought not to pay:</hi> namely, <hi>All</hi> Handy-crafts men that paid leſſe then the Tenth by the ſpace of 40. yeares before the Statute: <hi>All</hi> liuing vpon Fiſhing: <hi>All</hi> in <hi>London, Canterbury,</hi> and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14242:30"/> other Places hauing a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to pay a rate by their houſes: and Thoſe of <hi>Wales</hi> in that one Particular.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is euident that All others, though they haue not paid by 40. yeares before that Act, yet <hi>in right ought to pay.</hi> For, why elſe ſhould ſo many bee exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Name, if the purpoſe of the Statute were not to bind all others not ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. By the maine Scope and End of the Statute.</note>2. This appeares yet more cleerely by the Maine <hi>Scope and End</hi> of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, as is manifeſt to euery man (though no Lawyer) that ſhall read and obſerue it but with one of his Eyes.</p>
            <p>The Intent of a Law, (ſay our Great Maſters of the Law) is beſt diſcerned by the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir. The
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14242:30"/> Preface of this Statute hath reference to Two other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, one made in 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the other in 32. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. to the ſame purpoſe: and it ſaith, that <hi>diuers things are needfull to bee added to thoſe other Statutes, that Tithes may be truly paid according to the minde of the Law-makers,</hi> for which purpoſe this laſt Act was made. Wee muſt then conſider: 1. What was enacted: 2. What was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue in thoſe former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes: 3. What here is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. What was ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</note> In the former Statute of 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. it was reſolued that as well <hi>Perſonall</hi> as Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall Tithes were <hi>due vnto God and Holy Church:</hi> and therefore enacted that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubiect ſhould pay them <hi>according to the Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14242:31"/> Lawes and Ordinances of the Church of England, and after the laudable vſages and cuſtomes of the place where he dwelleth.</hi> The Statute of 32. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. was principally intended both to giue life to the former Statute, and alſo to enable Lay-men enioying Tithes to recouer them by Law, which, before they could not.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. What was defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue.</note>2. Neither of thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes did particularly decree what <hi>Praedial</hi> Tithes ſhould be due; from what Ground: and in what Quantitie in ſome Grounds: what Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes ſhould hold, and what not: What Places and Perſons ſhould allow <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall</hi> Tithes, and what not: nor how much ſhould bee due, where no Cuſtome, Compoſition real, or other
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14242:31"/> ſufficient Priuiledge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kes place.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All theſe Defects are ſupplyed in this Statute of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 6. For, (paſſing ouer the ſupplies touching P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Tithes) wee may finde theſe ſupplies for <hi>Perſonal</hi> Tithes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereas the former Statutes ſpake of them only in Groſſe; <hi>This</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth of what in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular they ſhall ariſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas the former did not expreſſe the iuſt Quantity exactly; <hi>This</hi> ſaith, the Tenth of cleere gaines.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. What is ſupplied.</note> Whereas the former did ſpeake of Cuſtomes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ally; <hi>This</hi> ſhewes where, and in what Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and to what Quantity Cuſtome ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l preuaile to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14242:32"/> paying leſſe then a Tenth, and in what not.</p>
            <p>This Statute agreeth to the beſt Engliſh Canon Law made and eſtabliſhed for declaring, and paying of Tithes both Praedial and Perſonal, aboue 320. yeares ſithence: Only this Statute of <hi>Edw.</hi> giues more to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and to ſome Perſons, then that ancient Law doth. Now, it is granted that ſo much of the Canon Law as is not againſt ſome Statute in force, is ſtill good Law. In the particular of Tithes, it is ratified by the Lawes of the Kingdome. What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Statute of <hi>Edward the ſixth</hi> hath not cut off from that old Conſtitution, it hath eſtabliſhed for Law.</p>
            <p>To make this cleare to euery eye, doe but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14242:32"/> theſe things: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſaith thus; <hi>Be it or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned and enacted by the King, &amp;c. that the ſaid Acts made in the</hi> 27. <hi>and</hi> 32. <hi>yeares of the reigne of the late King</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning true payment of Tithes, and euery article and branch therin contained, ſhall abide and ſtand in their full ſtrength and vertue.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what euer was enioyned in thoſe former Statutes, is by this Statute eſtabliſhed to continue in full force.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider that the Statute of 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. doth in expreſſe termes ordaine payment as well of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal as Praedial Tithes <hi>according to the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Lawes and Ordinances of the Church of England and after the</hi> Laudable vſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14242:33"/> 
               <hi>and cuſtomes of</hi> each Pariſh. And in that other Statute of 32. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the ſame was againe enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſtill hauing reference for kinde and Quantitie to the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Lawes,</hi> &amp; <hi>lawfull Cuſtomes.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what euer was then payable by the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Lawes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (vnleſſe in ſome Pedulia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s where Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes laudable and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full had taken root) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time in vſe, was eſtabliſhed by thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and ſo reeſtabliſhed by the Statute of <hi>Edward the ſixth,</hi> to remaine in force as the Law of the Realme to euery Place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14242:33"/> this, (as it is to be ſeene in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>INDVVOOD: <hi>Prouinc: Conſtitut: tit: de Doc: c. Quon: Prop:</hi>) that<note n="*" place="margin">Statuimus etiam quod Dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mae perſonales ſoluantur de artiſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoribus, ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licet de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiationis. Similiter de carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris, cem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tariis, tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus, pandoxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricibus, &amp; omnibus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ijs ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dariis: vt videlicet dent Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas de ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, niſi ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendarii i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi aliquid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lint dare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d opus, vel ad lumen Eccleſiae, ſi Rectori ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae placue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> 
               <hi>Perſonal Tithes ſhould be paid from Artificers, and Tradeſmens gaine of Trading. And ſo from Carpenters, Smiths, Plaiſterers, Weaners, Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and all other Labourers who ſhould all pay the Tenth of their Wages.</hi> This Canon was made at a Convocation Wolden at London in 23. <hi>Edward:</hi> 1. And is rightly reaconed, by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Selden,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of the Engliſh <hi>Canon</hi> Lawes. It is the Principall Rule and Law for ſundry Tithes, therein (and no where elſe) expreſſed, which hath force to this Day from the Statutes aforeſaid, as daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14242:34"/> ſheweth.</p>
            <p>From the Premiſſes theſe Concluſions doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyably iſſue.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtory of Tithes. cap. 8. pag, 232.</note>1. That in all Places Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Tithes of right ought to be paid where any Lawes enacted within 40. yeares before the Statute of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſixth</hi> hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded their Payment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all Perſonall Tithes decreed to be paid in thoſe two Statutes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. are ſtill due of right; both becauſe they were made within 16. yeares before that of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. and becauſe this laſt Statute doth ratifie thoſe, and euery branch of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all Perſonall Tithes that of right ought to be paid by the ſpace of 24. yeares before either of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14242:34"/> thoſe Statutes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. are ſtill due; becauſe the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. were made but 16. yeares at moſt before that of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. and this Statute extendeth to 40. yeares backe-ward.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That all Perſonall Tithes due by the old Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non before mentioned, are due by the Lawes of this Realme: foraſmuch as the Statutes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie that Canon, and the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. doth ratifie thoſe Statutes, except before excepted.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That therefore the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Edward:</hi> 6. (giuing force to the old Law which enioyned the payment of Perſonal Tithes,) doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and commaund that the Tenth part of euery mans cleare Gaines (except
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14242:35"/> ſuch as are expreſſely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſaid Statute,) ſhould bee paid by euery man to his Miniſter.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That it is not needfull for the Miniſter to proue (if he will recouer or demaund Perſonal Tithes where they were neuer paid,) that ſuch Tithes haue beene conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or at all paid in the Place where hee liueth, by the ſpace of 40. yeares before the Statute; ſince the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute maketh them due, where, <hi>of right they ought to be paid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the Right bee cleare enough; yet to make all men ſee it with both eyes without Spectacles, I will reduce all that hath beene ſpoken to proue the right of Perſonal Tithes, into forme, thus.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:14242:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>There Perſonal Tithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of right ought to be paid by vertue of the Statute of Edward the ſixth, where there was any right to them within</hi> 40. <hi>yeares before that Statute, although they were not actuacty paid.</hi> But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was in all places a right vnto Perſonal Tithes by</hi> 40. <hi>yeares before that Statute, though they were not actually paid.</hi> Therefore <hi>in all Places (not expreſſely excepted in the Statute of Edward th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſixth) Perſonal Tithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought ſtill to bee paid though it cannot be proued that they were actually paid in all that time.</hi> The <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> is proued, thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There muſt needs be a Right to pay Perſonal Tithes, where any Statutes
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14242:36"/> ſtill in force, enacted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> 40. <hi>yeares before that Statute of Edward, enioyne the payment of Perſonal Tithes.</hi> But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both thoſe Statutes of Hen.</hi> 2. <hi>enioyned the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Perſonal Tithes, and were enacted within</hi> 40. <hi>yeares of that laſt Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and are ſtill in force:</hi> Therfore <hi>Perſonal Tithes,</hi> that is, <hi>the Tenth of euery mans cleere gaines, are ſtill due and of right ought to be paid by all Perſons, and in all places not expreſſely exempted by Statute, though it cannot bee proued that they were euer actually paid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſhould ſay; <hi>Where the Cuſtome of the Place hath beene to pay nothing, nothing is due.</hi> This will appeare to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14242:36"/> be a meere Cauil, by that one Maxime knowne to Al of any experience or obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. <hi>De non Soluendis de cimis non valet conſuetudo.</hi> Cuſtome of paying no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, is worth nothing. The reaſon giuen by Lawyers is, <hi>iuri naturae &amp; diuino contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria eſt.</hi> Becauſe it is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry both to the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and God himſelfe. The Law in ſuch a caſe is this; Where men pay no Tithes at all of any thing made Tithable by any Law, there Tithes (vnleſſe ſome ſpeciall Priuiledge allowed by Law bee pleaded and proued) muſt be paid to the vtmoſt extent that any Law hath decreed ſuch Tithes to bee paid in any place. So then, He that confeſſeth he neuer paid any thing, nor that it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14242:37"/> hath beene the Cuſtome of the Place where he liueth ſo to doe, maketh himſelfe liable to pay the full Tenth.</p>
            <p>Leaſt any man ſhould ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect me of ignorance, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie in this point, becauſe I ſeeme out of my element: I will produce M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Selden</hi> (none of the beſt Proctors for vs Tithing-men, but One with whom we poore Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars are daily noſed,) to bruſh off this aſperſion, if any be caſt on mee.</p>
            <p>He, in his <hi>History of Tithes, Cap.</hi> 20. ſhewing that <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries</hi> firſt became due vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the generall preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euery mans negligence in paying his <hi>Perſonal</hi> Tithes in his life time, (for which cauſe a Mortuary was giuen in lieu of ſuch Tithes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid at death:) hee alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14242:37"/> a Caſe adiudged in it. <hi>Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rd,</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wherein the Perſon of <hi>Whitwell</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſped for taking away a Horſe for a Mortuary at the death of one of his Pariſh, according to the ancient Cuſtome of the Land and Holy Church, was acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the Plaintiffe, and his Act iuſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Law.</p>
            <p>This he vrgeth to proue, that Cuſtome hath euer beene held as Law, euen for ſuch Perſonal Tithes. But he explaineth himſelfe thus; <hi>Where any Statute hath made a diſcharge, or Preſcription, or Cuſtome hath ſetled a</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, de cimandi <hi>or certaine Quantitie payable, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo little, for the Tith, there, by the Lawes of the Kingdome, the Owner is not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14242:38"/> bound to pay other Tith then the Statute, or Cuſtome, or Preſcription binds him to. Which yet muſt bee ſo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the Caſe of Lay-men, that Cuſtome or Preſcription founded in their Poſſeſsions as Lay, cannot wholly diſcharge the Tith, or bee</hi> De non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimando, <hi>but may well bee</hi> De modo <hi>only. Otherwiſe is it in the caſe of Spiritual Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that may by the Common Law be by Preſcription whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharged, and preſcribe</hi> De non decimando. AND THIS IS REGVLAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY CLEERE LAVV. Thus, that Maſter of the Law.</p>
            <p>This conſidered, doth fully plucke vp another ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection by the rootes which any wrangler might make from thoſe Phraſes in the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14242:38"/> Statutes of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. which ſay, men ſhall pay their Tithes according to the laudable and lawfull vſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and cuſtomes of the Places wherein they liue. Thoſe Cuſtomes are neither laudable, nor lawfull which are pleaded for paying of nothing. It is not ſaid that where any Cuſtome hath beene to pay nothing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be paid: but, men ſhall pay their Tithes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the laudable vſages and cuſtomes of each place where they liue. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be vnderſtood of Cuſtomes by which men doe <hi>Pay</hi> ſomething: All being tyed to <hi>Pay;</hi> and all Cuſtomes of <hi>paying noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng</hi> being vtterly voide. To ſay, that Law, which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds ſome men <hi>to pay,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14242:39"/> according to Cuſtome</hi> doth ſhow the ſame men to plead Cuſtome for <hi>paying nothing,</hi> is a Contradiction very ridiculous.</p>
            <p>But yet ſome may ſay: <hi>If the Law bee ſo firme for Perſonal Tithes, How is it that</hi> Miniſters <hi>call not, for them, and that they doe not recouer them by Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I may anſwere with <hi>Griefe.</hi> That Law which hath made them due, hath giuen vs power enough to recouer them of euery man that is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and makes conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not to lie, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue; but it hath not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs ſtrength ſufficient to recouer them if they bee denyed by a Knaue: for it debarreth vs of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and indeed the only
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14242:39"/> meanes of finding out what euery diſhoneſt mans gaines are: namely, <hi>the Oath of the partie that is to pay them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Makers of this Law ſuppoſing Tradeſmen bred in Townes to haue more Giui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> then others, and preſuming of their hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and conſcionableneſſe to pay their dues to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, without ſuites in Law; did purpoſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that the Tradeſman ſhould not bee forced to diſcouer his Eſtate to the World ſo oft as otherwiſe (in likely-hood) hee ſhould bee required; which might proue much to his preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was their Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to enioyne the dutie without binding him to this extremitie: but it was their
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14242:40"/> purpoſe to tie his conſcience the more to doe iuſtly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as he will anſwer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary at his perill to God, to whom they leaue him for puniſhment. Elſe why ſhould they make ſuch a law to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what was due, and command the <hi>payment at Eaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that ſhall ſay, I am not bound by Law, where the Law hath omitted any one way to compell mee, doth moſt impiouſly abuſe the Lenitie of the Magiſtrate, and beleeues the Magiſtrate doth neuer command till he ſmite. In Diuinity it is no better then Hereſie, (if it be ſtood vnto;) and in Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no better then ſowing the ſeeds of Sedition and curſed Rebellion, to hold, <hi>That no Law hath any force to binde,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14242:40"/> but where it giues power to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh:</hi> And that <hi>the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates word ſhall bee void, where his ſword doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low at the heeles: nor ought to bee longer obeyed, then hee is fighting, or putting weapons into other mens hands.</hi> It is a thouſand pitties they ſhould want blowes who will doe nothing without them. When the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Law was not made for the righteous, but for the Lawleſſe, and diſobedient;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.6.</note> he meant, (as I thinke you will grant,) that the curſe and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Law was not intended to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, becauſe hee would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it ſo carefully, that there ſhould be no need of Compulſories to be ſeru'd vpon Him. But doth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle thereby exclude him
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14242:41"/> from the commaundement and Rule of the Law? Who but an Epicure, or Mad-man would make ſuch a Gloſſe? When God gaue authoritie to the Husband to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand his Wife in lawfull things; but not to beat her: ſhall the Wife ſhake off the yoke of obedience which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Husband; and ſay, <hi>God neuer meant that Law by which my Husband ſeekes to command me, ſhould binde mee; becauſe he hath denyed him power, to compell me by ſtripes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What though the Statute deny vs the oath of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet it commands <hi>payment at Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi> in expreſſe termes: and giues power to ſue him and to examine him by all other lawfull and reaſonable meanes: ſo as he ſhall bee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14242:41"/> compelled to ſpeake trueth, or falſhood. The Ordinary may compell him to <hi>ſay</hi> what he hath gained, though he cannot compell him <hi>to ſweare.</hi> This indeed makes ſome difference when a man is to deale with a falſe Knaue: but none at all when he is to deale with honeſt conſcientious men. And if the Statute had giuen vs the <hi>Oath</hi> of the Party; vnleſſe we could get another Statute enacted, not onely to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne, but to make all men to be <hi>Honeſt;</hi> our caſe would be but little yea very little b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tter then it is. I need ſay no more to Reaſonable men: yet one thing more, which makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ow, that the Statute doth binde all men to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y Perſonall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thus, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:14242:42"/> Oath of the Party. The Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute doth not onely giue power to the Ordinary to examine a Tradeſman, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; but alſo to order him according to what the party ſhall confeſſe, or can be otherwiſe proued, (as in Predial Tythes,) or elſe to excommunicate him for his contumacy; &amp; afterwards, to require a Writ out of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery <hi>De Excommunicato ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendo,</hi> if the Party ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his contempt for the ſpace of forty Daies.</p>
            <p>But, what if it ſhould be granted that Tradeſmen are not preciſely and formally bound by that Statute, as Husbandmen are? What would they gaine to iuſtifie themſelues in point of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Conſcience? Let them ſuppoſe themſelues
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14242:42"/> free from the Law in the ſtrictneſſe and rigour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; yet they muſt confeſſe the Husbandman to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely bound to a Tenth. Nor will any but Browniſts and Rebels deny the Power of the Parliament to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point that Quantitie. Now the Law binding the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, doth as firmely, in equitie binde Tradeſmen to the ſame proportion, if they will not hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Lawleſſe, but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themſelues bound to that Law which bindeth the reſt of their Brethren.</p>
            <p>There be two things that binde to a dutie: <hi>Iustice,</hi> and <hi>Equitie</hi> the ground of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. In <hi>Iuſtice</hi> (as it is ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken) he onely is bound on whom the Law eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed doth abſolutely, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14242:43"/> and expreſly take hold, and commandeth him <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally.</hi> But in <hi>Equitie,</hi> which is the ground of Law, euery man liuing in the ſame State is <hi>truly</hi> bound alſo, to whom the ſame Equitie on which the Law enacted was built, equally extendeth.</p>
            <p>To ſhut vp all. From all that hath beene ſaid, I may iuſtly draw foure <hi>Concluſions</hi> more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whoſoeuer gaineth by Trade, bargaining, or other lawfull meanes, being not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted as aforeſaid, muſt pay the Tenth of his cleere gaines, or he ſinneth againſt the lawes of this Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whoſoeuer in this caſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olateth the lawes of this Realme, is a double ſinner againſt the law of God: for he breaketh that Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14242:43"/> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſhalt not Steale: and committeth Sacriledge by with-holding that which lawfull Authoritie hath law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully conſecrated to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Although a man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy part of his ſtocke in Husbandry; yet is hee bound to pay the Tith of his Gaines by Trading (if hee vſe any) as well as if he paid no Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Tithes at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>They who being infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of this Dutie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inced in their iudgement thereof, are bound to Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution (vnleſſe their Paſtors remit it) of all they haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto wrongfully deteined ſo neere, and as full as they are able. Otherwiſe, they wickedly; robbe the Miniſter, and liue in a damnable ſinne without repentance: nor can they in ſuch a condition ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14242:44"/> any thing from God but wrath and a curſe vpon them and theirs, let their Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and forwardneſſe in other duties of Religion be what it will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I expect many to cry out vpon this, as <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>hard Doctrine:</hi> and to ſay, <hi>If wee ſhould pay all Arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, wee ſhould part, it may bee, with halfe our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</hi> But then I muſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: to the firſt part, if it bee true, (as you ſee it is;) the ſtrangeneſſe of it muſt not make any man bold to <hi>kicke against the Pricks.</hi> And to the latter, I ſay.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is vnlikely and vnprobable that the Tenth part of a mans cleere gaines ſhould bee halfe his eſtate both of Stocke and Gaines.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:14242:44"/>2. Admit it were ſo, yet if what thou detei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt be none of thine, it will make a greater hole in thy conſcience, then it can in thine eſtate by parting with it. The V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer and the Theefe haue as good a Plea as this againſt Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Zacheus</hi> did as much, and our Sauiour appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it as one ſigne that proued him <hi>A ſonne of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham:</hi> Grace will make men iuſt; though it ſhould make them as poore as <hi>Lazarus.</hi> Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution with an ouer-plus, if they be able, ſhall be vnto them, as any other dutie enioyned by God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If God haue blowne vpon thy diſhoneſt gaine;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14242:45"/> and made thee vnable to Reſtitution; then behold his hand; humble thy ſelfe euen vnto Hell for this ſinne; and deſire of God, one way or other to repaire the wrongs, that cannot bee repaired by thy ſelfe. And in this caſe, hee were an hard and moſt vnconſcionable Miniſter that ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Let not Reſtitution then be held an uniuſt and cruel impoſition. And for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tithes for time to come, ſticke not at it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou now ſeeſt it to bee thy dutie: doe it cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, leaſt God account it as not done at all.</p>
            <p>Conſider (beſides all the former diſcourſe) this one thing: Hee that willingly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14242:45"/> and iuſtly payes the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Portion hath a more ſpeciall promiſe of God to thriue in his Calling, then any man hath, for perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of any one other particular dutie whatſoeuer. The Promiſe I meane is in <hi>Malachy</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. and it is this; <hi>Bring yee all the Tithes into the Store-houſe that there may bee meat in mine houſe, and proue mee now herewith, ſaith the Lord of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſts, if I will not open you the windowes of heauen, and powre you out a bleſsing, that there ſhall not bee roome enough to receiue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I will rebuke the deuourer for your ſake, and he ſhall not deſtroy the fruit of your ground, neither ſhall your v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne caſt her fruit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time in the field,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14242:46"/> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. And all nations ſhall call you bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for yee ſhall be a delight ſome land, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now hee that doth not obey this iniunction, (at leaſt ſo farre as now by Law he is tyed) doth, thereby proclaime that hee doth not beleeue this promiſe: Hee ſaith in his heart that in this point God is a Lyer, and it is in vaine to ſerue him.</p>
            <p>One Scruple yet is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. Some may ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; <hi>It may bee my Miniſter is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, vnfaithfull, or ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: muſt hee haue Tenths too?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though ſuch a perſon deſerue them not, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing actually poſſeſſed of the Church (and preſumed in Law to bee ſuch as hee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14242:46"/> ought) hee may claime them as due in the right of the Church, vntill Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſhall take notice of his demerit, and diſcharge the Church of ſuch a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
            <p>So then; He that ſought to wind himſelfe out of the brakes of Tithes due by <hi>Diuine Right,</hi> ſuppoſing it better to ſtand to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Diſcretion, may ſee what a fine Snare hee hath made for himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Hee, muſt not heare of Tithes due by the Old Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. The Magiſtrate muſt giue him his Rule. Well. A Law is now eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This Law binds eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to giue the Tenth of his cleare Gaines to his Miniſter. It makes no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption of Bad Miniſters.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14242:47"/> Therefore The Tradeſman is bound in Conſcience and by Law to pay Tithes to his Miniſter be he Good or bad: or his owne Rule will caſt him for a Sinner.</p>
            <p>If I owe mony to a Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, I may not iuſtifie the deteining of it, when it was due, becauſe I know he will abuſe it to more drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ryot, and other ſinnes againſt God. I may labour his Reformation by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, but may not deny him his dues. His diſorder cannot warrant me to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt. The Law for Tithes makes them as due to the Miniſter, as Law can make them: and ſuppoſing that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Patron and Biſhop will be carefull to place none in any liuings but ſuch as are worthy: it exempts none
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14242:47"/> from the exhibition of the Place to which they are inducted. Therefore the Tradeſman or any other cannot without Theft and Sacriledg deny any Miniſter his dues, ſo long as he ſtands poſſeſſed of the Church, and in the relation of a Paſtor vnto him. If any man haue iuſt exception againſt his Miniſter, they know <hi>the Law is open, and there be Iudges, let them implead one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Whoſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all. <bibl>
                     <hi>Iam. 2.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Thou that abhorreſt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols doeſt thou commit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge. <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 2.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
